Andrés Isaza Giraldo

+351 926 857 988 isazag@gmail.com http://isaza.xyz

Media artist born in Manizales, Colombia. He has directed the short-films *Medias blancas* (2017), *Sereno* (2022) and *The Last Film on Earth* (2023), alongside several music videos, video-essays and interactive experiences. He has an interest in video post-production and machine learning technologies. His work explores the relationship of time in life, history, landscape and cinema.

EDUCATION

2024 Master in Multimedia Arts, Moving Image Specialization,

Fine Arts Faculty, University of Lisbon, Lisbon, Portugal

Thesis: "Fluid Mirrors: Filming the Rivers of the Future" Grade: 19/20

2017 Bachelor with honors in Film and Television Making

Arts Faculty, National University of Colombia, Bogota, Colombia

AWARDS, GRANTS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Grants, Funding and Scholarships

2023	ALIFE2023: A Ghost in the Machine, Conference Studentship, full travel support and conference registration, Sapporo, Japan
2023	Research Grant from Câmara Municipal de Funchal - Portuguese Recovery and Resilience Program (PRR), Funchal, Portugal
2022	Research Initiation Grant from Agência Regional para o Desenvolvimento da Investigação, Tecnologia e Innovação ARDITI, Funchal, Portugal
2020	Colfuturo Scolarship
2018	Fondo para el Desarrollo Cinematográfico (FDC) - Estímulo para la Realización de Cortometrajes de Ficción (8 winers among 282 participants)
2018	Beca de Curaduría Audiovisual, Collective Project) (1 winner over 7)
2016	Winner of the fund 'Beca Cinemateca para Creación de Cortometraje de Ficción Alternativo 2016' of Idartes (Distrital Institute for the Arts, Bogota)

Awards and mentions

2023	Special Mention at DO(C)ÔA Nature Film Festival, vila de Foz Côa, Portugal
2022	Best National Short Film, Bugarte Film and Visual Arts Festival, Colombia
2022	Special Mention in the Regional Short-Film category, Festival Internacional
	de Cine de Riosucio, Colombia
2021	Best Videoclip, Sobre Ruedas 2021, Manizales, Colombia
2018	Winner first place National short film at 10° Maratón de Cortometrajes
	Pantalones Cortos, Medellín, Colombia

2018 Special mention in 3 Eureka Festival Universitario de Cine, Bogota, Colombia 2018 Special mention Official Student Section at Festival Cortos Cali 2018, Cali, Colombia Winner Best Fiction Short Film at Premios Corte Final in Pereira, Colombia 2018 Winner Short Film Writing Workshop in BIFF 2016 (Bogota International Film 2016 Festival). 2016 Winner of Malpensante Prize, Film Critic and Journalism Workshop at Festival Internacional de Cine de Cartagena de Indias (FICCI), Cartagena 2014 Winner of Best Proyect, Short-film Documentary Project Laboratory, Festival Equinoxio, Bogota

SELECTED FESTIVALS AND SCREENINGS

2024	International Competition - 37° Stuttgarter Filmwinter, Stuttgart, Germany
2024	"AI: Dreams, Fantasies and Bodies", West Virginia Mountaineer Short Film
	Festival, United States
2024	"Cuerpo de un tercer mundo" by Porosa Animación at Cinemateca de
	Bogotá, Bogota, Colombia
2024	Autopsia Bogota Experimental Film Festival, Bogota, Colombia
2023	Iberoamerican Short Film Competition – Festival Internacional de Cine de la
	Universidad de Buenos Aires FIC.UBA, Buenos Aires, Argentina
2023	Official International Selection, Festival Internacional de Medios Alternativos,
	Mexico City, Mexico
2023	Experimental National Competition, Bogotá International Short Film Festival,
	Colombia
2022	Official Selection, Cartagena de Indias International Film Festival FICCI,
	Cartagena, Colombia
2022	International Competition, Beijing International Short Film Festival, Beijing, China
2022	Central Showcase, Cinemancia Metropolitan Film Festival, Valle de Aburrá
0000	Metropolitan Area, Colombia
2022 2022	Regional Selection, Andares Contemporary Film Festival, Lima, Peru National Selection, Cali Short Film Festival, Cali, Colombia
2022	Programa Premio Dunkel Rosa 2020, Ciclo Rosa; Bogota, Medellín and Cali;
2021	Colombia
2019	Showcase Best Graduation Films from Escuela de Cine y TV - Universidad
	Nacional de Colombia at UNAL FEST
2018	Showcase '30 años de la Escuela de Cine y Televisión de la Universidad
	Nacion al de Colombia at 16 Bogotá International Short Film Festival, Bogota, Colombia
2018	National Competition, 10 Festival Internacional de Cine de Cali FICCALI,
20.0	Cali, Colombia
2018	FICU - Festival Internacional de Cine Universitario, Buenos Aires, Argentina
2018	Caleidoscopio Short Film Competition, 3er Festival de Cine al Jardín, Jardín,
0040	Colombia Official Colombia 44 CINETORO Functional Films Footistal Target
2018	Official Selection, 11 CINETORO Experimental Film Festival, Toro, Colombia
	Odombia

2018	Selection Aciertos, Festival Internacional de la Universidad Autónoma de
	México FICUNAM 2018, Mexico City, Mexico
2018	Selection Film (&) Digital, XVII International Image Festival, Manizales,
	Colombia
2017	Fiction Panorama, 15 Bogota International Short Film Festival, Bogota,
	Colombia

EXHIBITIONS

2024	Galerias Abertas, Faculdade de Belas-Artes, Lisbon, Portugal
2024	Politics of Machines: Lifelikeness and Beyond, Aachen, Germany
2023	Artificio exhibition, Fundación Gilberto Alzate Avendaño, Bogota, Colombia
2022	RareEffect Vol. 3, Lisbon, Portugal

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Conferences and Extended Abstracts

Isaza-Giraldo, Andrés; Paulo Bala; Pedro F. Campos; and Lucas Pereira.

"Prompt-Gaming: A Pilot Study on LLM-Evaluating Agent in a Meaningful Energy Game" in *Extended Abstracts of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA '24)*. Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 272, 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1145/3613905.3650774

Isaza-Giraldo, Andrés; Manuel Pereira; Rafael Candeias; and Lucas Pereira."Satellite Dataset Visual Analysis for Remote Soil Nutrient Estimation" in *Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference on Water Energy Food and Sustainability* (ICoWEFS 2023), Leiria, Portugal

https://www.alspereira.info/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ICoWEFS-2023.pdf

Book Chapters

Ardila, Andrés; Andrés Isaza; and Sara Fernández. "Un mundo sin adultos y la política de la amistad" in *Catálogos Razonados*, Cinemateca de Bogotá, [to be published]

Articles in Periodic Publications

Isaza Giraldo, Andrés. Simón Bolívar, Lucas Ochoa, Fernando González y yo. *Revista Cazamoscas, Revista Filosófica,* 12(13), pp. 62-72, 2022 https://issuu.com/revistacazamoscas/docs/czm13

Isaza Giraldo, Andrés. "La elevación paramuna" in *Revista Correspondencias: Mística // Año 05 // No. 15 // Invierno 2021*, Ciudad de México, 2021 http://correspondenciascine.com/2021/03/la-elevacion-paramuna/

Online publications

Isaza-Giraldo, A. Featured Project: "The Last Film on Earth". *ALife Newsletter Vol. 13*, October 2023

https://tinyurl.com/AlifeVol13

Ardila Ardila, Andrés Felipe; Andrés Isaza; Andrés Suárez; Angélica Hoyos; Alirio Cruz Cabrera; Camilo Villamizar Plazas; Daniel Mateo Vallejo Gutiérrez; Henry Melo, Javier Segovia, Jesús Gómez Giovanetti; Jonas Radziunas, Laura Huertas Millán, Luis Esguerra, Manuel Villa, María Paula Jiménez, Natalia Imery, Pablo Roldán, Santiago Henao Vélez and Sara Fernández. *MANIFIESTO por un (nuevo) cine CUIR en Colombia* in the blog Pajarera del Medio, Bogotá, 2018

http://pajareradelmedio.blogspot.com/2018/07/manifiesto-por-un-nuevo-cine-cuiren.html

Días extraños y las óperas primas latinoamericanas, juveniles, radicales, universitarias y en blanco y negro in the blog Micropsia Cine, Buenos Aires. 2016 [https://www.micropsiacine.com/2016/03/cartagena-2016-dias-extranos-y-las-operas-primas-latinoamericanas-juveniles-radicales-universitarias-y-en-blanco-y-negro/]

Video-essays

Pepa Jambrina (Pseudonim of Andrés Ardila and Andrés Isaza). *Hacerse el marica*. Presented in the Ciclo Rosa; Bogota, Medellin, Cali and Manizales, Colombia. 2021 https://vimeo.com/477482697/cdc30e6110

Zuluaga, Pedro Adrián and Andrés Isaza Giraldo. "Homo Videns" comissioned introduction to the exhibition *Luis Ospina: el corolario es casi inevitable, 1970-2019*, online, Fundación Gilberto Alzate Avendaño, Bogota, 2020 https://luisospinaelcorolarioescasinevitable19702019.reemplaz0.org/introduccion/

Articles Under Review

Andrés Isaza-Giraldo, Paulo Bala, Pedro F. Campos, and Lucas Pereira. "How Difficult is it to EN-JOIN?: Modulating Difficulty of LLM-Evaluator Agents that Play Characters in an Energy Community Game" - Short-paper submitted to conference

Manuscripts in Preparation

Andrés Isaza-Giraldo. "The Last Film on Earth: Simulating Historical Body in a Post-Human Computer" - Full paper in preparation for Politics of Machines Aachen: Lifelikeness and Beyond Conference 2024 Proceedings

CONFERENCES, TALKS AND WORKSHOPS

Communications at Conferences

One Last Film for the End of Times: Teaching a Computer What Sacrality Is Using Evo-Devo Speculation, Diffusion Models and Fiction at Explorations of Sound and New Media Art Conference, Escola de Artes UPC, Porto (Portugal), November 2023

Invited Talks

Writing Poetry for Machines Workshop at 2° Encontro de Educação Digital no Ensino Superior - Instituto Politecnico de Lisboa, Lisbon, July 2024

Prompt-gaming at ITI Talks, Interactive Technologies Institutes, Lisbon, March 2024

La Otraparte del Audiovisual: Sereno, Casa Museo Otraparte, Medellín, December 2023 https://www.voutube.com/watch?v=bAJr -S7LRs

Al Creativity Workshop at act.3 and FEEDERS, Lisbon (Portugal), May 2023

Aprendizaje de Máquina para Realizadores Audiovisuales (Machine Learning for Filmmakers) at Secretaría de Cultura de Caldas, Manizales, Colombia, May 2020 https://youtu.be/WhXmDA4X-kl?si=n0qiYUnw5uN_WfZo

Imágenes desde el Nordeste (*Images from the Northeast*) en Club Ornitorrinco, Online, April 2020 https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eaoXPI8R7mk

Taller de Percepción Sonora en el Cine (Sound Perception in Cinema Workshop) - Organized by Redespiral, Manizales, Colombia, December 2019

EXPERIENCE

Research Experience

June 2023 to present

Researcher, eGames Lab Project and Further Energy and Environment Research Laboratory, Interactive Technologies Institute (ITI/LARSyS), Funchal and Lisbon, Portugal

- Designs an energy game to improve meaningful knowledge on sustainable energy communities, implementing an LLM-evaluating agent
- Evaluates performance and performs user testing

September to November 2022

Assistant Researcher, Further Energy and Environment Research Laboratory, Interactive Technologies Institute (ITI/LARSyS), Research Initiation Scholarship, Funchal and Lisbon, Portugal

- Analized a dataset for soil nutrient estimation
- Proposed new strategies for dataset extraction and augmentation

Professional Experience

2017 to present

Freelance audiovisual director and cinematographer

Has directed several music videos with up to 700k views on YouTube.

- Directed the making off of the Oscar short-listed film *Pájaros de Verano* (*Birds of Passage*) with the Wayuu indigenous people.
- Has directed photography for long feature documentaries and fiction short films.

2014 to present

Freelance image post-production

Has color graded several short-films, gallery videos and other content.

2019 to 2022

Freelance coordination in audiovisual productions and festivals

- Produced educational web-series through the Engineering Faculty of the National University of Colombia and worked as assistant director for several short-films.
- Served as Guest Office Co-coordinator for the 19 IndieLisboa International Film Festival and assistant programmer for the retrospective of the 20th anniversary of the Muestra Internacional Documental de Bogotá MIDBO.

BIBLIOGRAPHY

Gamba, Pablo. La última película y El mañana es un palacio de agua, In Los Experimentos Blog de Cine, Argentina, 2024

http://www.losexperimentoscine.blog/2024/01/la-ultima-pelicula-y-el-manana-es-un.html

Acosta Vinasco, Gustavo (Host). 'Sereno' (cortometraje de ficción); Encuentro em la radio con Andrés Isaza Giraldo (Director) (No. 175) in Paisaje Audiovisual [Radio Show and Audio Podcast]. Emisora Cultural de Pereira. November 8, 2022.

 $\underline{https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/gustavoacosta/episodes/Sereno-cortometraje-\underline{de-ficcin-Encuentro-en-la-radio-con-Andrs-Isaza-Giraldo-Director-e1q8kt8}$

Espinoza, Liseth. Sereno, un recorrido audiovisual por el Nevado del Ruiz, La Patria [Printed and online], Manizales, October 18, 2022.

https://www.lapatria.com/entretenimiento/sereno-un-recorrido-audiovisual-por-el-nevado-del-ruiz

Evaristo, Yasmine. Zerou a Netflix? Plataforma oferece centenas de filmes latino americanos de graça. Secionamos os indispensáveis. In *Music Non-Stop*, November 2020. São Paulo.

Osorio, Oswaldo. "10 pensamientos x 10 años" in *Revista Cero en Conducta: Especial de Cine Colombiano 2010-2019*. November 2020. Bogotá https://www.revistaceroenconducta.com/revistas/cero-en-conducta-especial-cine-colombiano/10-pensamientos-x-10-anos/

Ardila, A. 2019. El retorno a casa: crecer en el cine de Colombia. In *Encuentro Cátedra Cinemateca escrituras críticas del audiovisual latinoamericano*. [Ponencia] Bogotá, 2019 https://diariodelprincipio.tumblr.com/post/186164263194/el-retorno-crecer-en-el-cine-en-colombia-apuntes

Betancourt, Lorezna. "Un mundo sin adultos" una muestra de cine sobre los excesos de niños y jóvenes. In *Vice Colombia*, Bogota, October 2018 https://www.vice.com/es/article/mundo-sin-adultos-muestra-cineexcesos-ninos-jovenes/

CURATION AND JURY

Exhibitions juried

2021 24 Festival Universitario de Cine y Audiovisuales Equinoxio, Competencia

Internacional: Documental, Bogotá

Exhibitions curated

2021 20 International Image Festival

Universidad de Caldas, Manizales, Colombia Co-programmer section "Film (&) Digital"

2020 19 International Image Festival

Universidad de Caldas, Manizales, Colombia

Programmer section "Film (&) Digital"

2018 Showcase "Un mundo sin adultos"

Cinemateca de Bogota and Museo de Arte Moderno de Medellin, Bogota and

Medellin, Colombia

Co-programmer alongside Sara Fernández and Andrés Ardila

2015 18 Equinoxio University Film Festival

National University of Colombia, Bogota, Colombia

Chief programmer

OTHER

Professional organizations

Association for Computing Machinery (May 2024 – present) International Society for Artificial Life (June 2023 – June 2024)

Languages

Spanish - Native

English - IELTS Academic Overall Band Score: 7.5 - CEFR Level C1 (Feb. 2020)

Portuguese - Proficient

French - Basic